We decided to test, well, what about
What if we let you choose which day you
get that reminder? And counterintuitive
like that, you know, normally you would
think that friction is probably not a
good thing, but what we saw was that,
you know, that drew attention to the
fact that you can choose when you want
your reminder, and we're going to remind
you, and so you can decide to cancel
later. That buys us enough time so that
you wait till that fifth day or sixth
day to decide really, okay, am I getting
value out of this? And it was a really
great way to increase confidence in the
product that you're going to try. Hello,
I'm your host, David Barnard. Today's
conversation is shorter than usual and
will be featured in Revenue Cat's State
of Subscription Apps Report. Each
episode in this series will explore one
crucial topic and share actionable
insights from top subscription app
operators. With me today, Anmol Tiwari,
director of product at Duolingo. On the
podcast, I talk with Anmol about how
Duolingo prioritizes clarity over
persuasion on their paywalls, why they
offer users multiple free trials instead
of just one, and how adding friction to
their trial reminder flow actually
boosted conversions. Hey, Anmol, thanks
so much for joining me on the podcast
today. Hi, David. Yeah, really excited
to be here. Thank you for having me. So,
I had uh your chief product officer,
Jam, on the podcast recently and was so
fascinated talking to him about the free
trial dynamics and even having a free
trial for a freemium app. So, folks can
go back and listen to that episode if
they want to dig into some of those
lessons, but there was so much we didn't
have time to talk about, and so I
thought it would be fun to have you on
to kind of dig deeper into some of the
deeper lessons that Duolingo's learned
about freemium and free trials. So, I
wanted to start at a really high level.
What would you say is kind of a guiding
principle for Duolingo around trials and
and getting people to experience the
premium features? Yeah, I think, you
know, the first thing that comes to mind
is when you're trying to sell a product,
it's incredibly hard to tell you or even
like describe to a user what the value
proposition of that product is. Now, we
can do it through kind of like UX or
like certain copy or even an ad, but the
best way for a user to really know what
you get in a subscription is by trying
it. And we've seen it as such an
effective lever that when you're trying
to explain that you get unlimited energy
or no ads, the best way to kind of
experience that is by trying it. You're
not going to understand the benefit. And
so, for us, trials are really effective
lever to try and get people to adopt our
paid features. And then how do you
position that in a way that makes it
clear? One of the things that we've
learned is our goal is not to like
persuade users to try this. Our goal is
to give them clarity and confidence to
purchase. So, you know, the most
effective way for users to be able to
feel confident [snorts] to try a trial
is to know like well, what does that
really entail? And that is anything from
being able to explain in a timeline what
happens on which day of the trial. You
know, we've seen even if for example,
when you're on one plan and you want to
you move to a different plan trying to
be clear about like what what is how
much money are you going to get back?
The refunds. Clarity is so important.
And you know, very recently, a great
example of this is that we've had this
functionality where when you sign up for
a free trial, you'll get a reminder, a
notification sent to you on, you know,
about 2 days before your trial expires.
And we decided we decided to test well,
what about what if we let you choose
which day you get that reminder? And
counterintuitive like that, you know,
normally you would think that friction
is probably not a good thing, but what
we saw was that, you know, that drew
attention to the fact that you can
choose when you want your reminder, and
we're going to remind you, and so you
can decide to cancel later. That buys us
enough time so that you wait till that
fifth day or sixth day to decide really,
okay, am I getting value out of this?
And it was a really great way to
increase confidence in what you're in
the product that you're going to try.
Any other lessons around clarity and
copy? I know Duolingo's done a lot with
like multi-step paywalls. Seems like
another way to introduce clarity. Any
other lessons there? One of the things
that I think users of course also care
about is like not losing their progress.
And so, what we've seen is that users
are just much more likely to start a
trial when the decision or like when we
position it as like, well, you know, if
you run out of hearts or energy, if you
don't continue, you're going to
basically lose your progress. And I
think we've done it in a way that's like
balances kind of showing still some
sense of progress, but trying to
basically also indicate that, well, if
you pay gems or if you try start this
free trial now, that's going to
basically you you'll be able to kind of
maintain your progress and finish this
lesson. I think the other lesson the
other kind of big lesson that we have
seen is that there isn't no
one-size-fits-all.
A really great example of that is new
users versus current users. We know that
like when a user is brand new to
Duolingo, they're actually way more
likely to convert. And what we've
actually seen is that instead of trying
to just like, you know, take our
standard upsells that try and promote
Super Duolingo and just put them in the
onboarding flow. We found that it's much
better to actually make it contextual to
the onboarding. So, as an example, we
asked like, how do you want to learn or
how do you want to achieve your goals?
Is it with with ads or without ads? Or
do you want to learn faster or do you
want to just learn at the pace that you
are you prefer? And what we saw was that
when that is kind of positioned as part
of onboarding, we saw significantly
higher kind of optic rate. It was one of
our biggest wins last year.
And what it's telling us is that we
can't while we some standardization is
really helpful, especially if you think
about it like, you know, our purchase
flow, sometimes you need to be aware of
kind of who the user is and when you
know, what where are they are in their
life cycle. Yeah, that makes a lot of
sense. And what about trial duration?
Have you all experimented with like a
month-long free trial, 3-day free trial
all the way up and down the stack or
where where do you land on duration of
trial? We used to have a 2-week trial, I
think towards till the end of 2024. And
one of the things that we ended up doing
was we tested a shorter duration, 7
days. And we tested this with a couple
of different combinations, but um users
are usually eligible for multiple
trials. And when we tested reducing it,
we actually saw like two different
benefits. The first was, of course,
overall net, we saw more conversions
over time in combination with like
playing around with how many trials we
can offer to a user. But the second,
more much more valuable benefit was when
you start a trial and you have to wait
14 days for a user to convert, that
means that from an experimentation
perspective, you have to wait 14 days.
And so, we actually basically doubled
our experimentation velocity because now
instead of having to wait 14 days,
you're just you get your results in 7
days. And imagine that compounding over
an entire quarter or over 6 months or
over a year. It was an incredibly
powerful lever cuz we can start we can
know very quickly whether an experiment
is going to perform well or not. And
then if it's not performing, that's
great. We can actually decide, okay, we
can shut that down and move on to the
next one. So, I think that has been an
incredibly effective lever for us. You
were talking about multiple trials. Tell
me tell me more about how that works. Um
and especially in light of tactically,
you You Apple and anyone SKU will only
allow the intro free offer to be
eligible one time. So, then you probably
have some way of resetting that or
sending them a different skew or
something like that. So, it's not it's
not been typical and Apple doesn't
really make it easy, either. Why offer
multiple trials to users? What we've
realized is I mean, as with anything,
it's ultimately a question of like kind
of what's going to be the easiest for a
user to both basically feel confident in
trying something out, but also we've
also quickly realized that users are not
always in the same life cycle stage. And
so, there's advantages in having
multiple trials for us. The first is
it's effective for us because we can try
to understand, well, okay, maybe in the
first time you didn't fully get to
understand the benefits or maybe you
tried it and you weren't sure. Or or you
tried it and you were like super busy
that one week and didn't actually get to
experience it.
>> Exactly. And maybe you know, a simple
framing of all of this is that imagine
if I asked you as from a business
standpoint, right? Or even from a user
standpoint, you might benefit from
having trying a product over a long like
over multiple periods, but spread across
a little bit. And from a business
standpoint, it's better because now you
as a user have to decide four times,
three or four times, whether you want to
make this purchase or not. And of
course, you know, aggregated across
those, we we'd see that it's it's an
effective lever. The second point that I
want to make is
what we've seen is that of course, not
everyone is as comfortable to start a
trial or for whatever reason, there's a
lot of hesitation despite all the things
that we try and do to try and increase
clarity of when you're going to get a
reminder, etc. So, we have this concept
of a free taste and where we basically
can offer you a trial-like experience,
um which is 3 days, but with no strings
attached. You get 3 days of the service
and you end up you can try the try the
subscription tier super or max and at
the end of the day at the end of that
period you get to decide whether you
want to convert or not or during the
period you can decide whether you want
to convert or not. And that's been a
really effective lever for not just free
to paid but paid to paid because to your
point about Apple it's a little it's
quite difficult for it's we can't offer
a second another free trial when you're
already a paying subscriber. But what we
can do is we can offer you a free taste
and then still take you back to the
original subscription tier that you were
on and that's been a really effective
lever for us to like get people to try
our highest tier max with video calls
especially. One last point is and when
you think about free taste or free
trials it doesn't just extend to the
tiers of the whole product. Sometimes
you can even extend it to a single
individual feature. We have something
called a video call which is part of the
max tier and what we've tried to what
we've seen sometimes is offering just
enough free tastes of that video call
just in isolation little just one call
is actually not a bad way to try and get
people to try a feature and see if they
want to convert and we've seen that also
as an effective lever. Are there
what are the specific ways you make it
really clear that they're getting this
reverse trial is what it's typically
called in the industry where you don't
have a credit card and they actually
have to subscribe to get back to the
subscription state. How how do you make
that clear is there a countdown you know
what kind of copy is on the buttons cuz
this this something I know I've heard
from other folks who've done this I've
done some of this in my own app that I
run on the side and people expect it to
auto convert and they're they're even
like scared to like get that free taste
at least like I haven't been able to
crack it I haven't talked to many people
who've cracked being able to communicate
that effectively. Yeah well the first
thing is we usually always have copy
that makes it absolutely clear that this
is a three-day kind of free period or
free preview. I think preview is another
word phrasing that I've used in the
industry. The other thing is we actually
always position it as like a reward and
we say, "Hey, you just earned you just
earned this." And one of the things that
we used to initially have it on our, you
know, when you're learning through the
course there's a path there's a chest on
the path in your learning path. And
moved it towards after the lesson
because it felt more rewarding to earn
it after completing a lesson. And so, I
think when you position it as a reward,
it helps like signal that like, "Oh, I'm
getting this is just like a limited time
benefit." The other there are we do use
like kind of like some type of timers or
concepts of timers to help drive like
urgency when you go to the subscriptions
page, you'll also see that you can
upgrade anytime. But, it's super
important to like make sure that
consumers understand that this is not
going to suddenly charge you a different
amount. The one of the things that of
course we always you know, we talk about
clarity, but clarity also comes is super
important in just maintaining trust
because if suddenly users don't trust
what you're doing, then you know,
they're
will be way more skeptical. And I think
the risk in a product like where you're
paying for Super and you get a trial for
Max is, you know, they may even cancel
their Super. And we of course don't want
that, you know. So, and then I would
imagine the the paywall they land on
after a free taste looks different and
has different copy than like a
onboarding paywall. So, did does that
paywall say like, you know, did you
enjoy your three days? Like extend it
indefinitely or or like are there any
kind of copy wins you've had there that
kind of help, you know, remind people or
or reinforce that like loss aversion
you're going to lose this if you don't?
Like how do you position that after the
free taste? Yeah, usually after we We
always let users know I think it's like
a home drawer that comes up. I think one
of the things we just emphasize is that
your X benefits have ended. And then we
usually always give like kind of two
sets of options. One is either to
continue or to basically kind of explore
and or resubscribe. And I think that the
important thing there is that being
super clear that it's ended. And two,
we're drawing attention to the fact that
you can easily rejoin. What about
personalization? Are you doing any kind
of user level personalization on these
paywalls and offers and when they offer
the free trials and things like that?
Yeah, we've really ramped up I think our
investments in personalization using
machine learning to try and optimize a
host of things. As you know, we of
course our freemium or free tier is with
ads and those ads are a mix of kind of
ads that are promoting our subscription
products and also third-party ads
promoting websites, mobile other mobile
apps, etc. And
one of the first few things that we
tried starting to optimize was well,
what is the right mix of, you know,
promoting our own product versus serving
other external ads. And we saw good wins
on it. And then that that translates
also into now well, okay, now if we know
that you're likely to subscribe, we can
probably predict how likely are you to
subscribe to which plan. We used to have
like fixed ratios on how many ads we
show that are for like each tier, but
that's quite an inefficient way to
operate because we probably have a lot
of signals that we can leverage. Did you
ever tap on that plan in the past? Did
you try to learn more about video call
when we showed you the video call as
your next lesson? So for us we've seen
actually like a lot of great wins and
it's super important to kind of keep
collecting signals that can help you
personalize not just basically kind of
all aspects of like upsells. And I think
we are still we've just barely scratched
the surface of it. I think there's a lot
of like wins that we can go like just
getting all the way into for example, we
have many many creatives that run to
promote our super product as an ad at
the end of a lesson. And we've had some
wins in having a bandit and trying to
optimize which creative will work best
for who. And we're continuing to see
wins from that. Yeah, that's awesome.
And
always fun to hear that I have a
Duolingo scale is still early in some of
the optimizations that we all wish we
had time and budget and teams to work
on. It's really cool to hear the the
wins you have seen on personalization in
the app. I want to wrap up with
something you actually taught me when we
were preparing for the podcast and
that's that free trials aren't actually
common everywhere around the world and
that you do need to take into account
the way certain countries are used to
buying things. So tell me more about
what you learned there. I think free
trials are really kind of a not
necessarily a universal concept. They're
getting better understood over time, but
they are always going to be regional
differences, whether that's for like
payment method reasons, regulation
reasons, or just consumer preferences.
China is a great example. Almost every
single subscription service doesn't
really offer a free trial that's
absolutely zero dollars to try. They
actually prefer a model in which you
have to pay a very small nominal amount
to get access to a trial. Let's just say
like a dollar or 99 cents. And that
quite interesting because one the
reasons behind this is of course
cultural nuances play out. People are
not familiar with this auto renewal
concept. And two is paid trials is quite
interesting because they are actually
trying to do something which is similar
in what we're talking about in terms of
trying to add clarity that this is a
paid product. So, you know, back to my
really original point about clarity over
persuasion, it's you'll see that like
it's so important to make sure that
people understand what they're going to
be trying or buying ultimately. You
know, you want to be clear that there is
going to be a annual charge or a monthly
charge after your trial that's going to
happen on a recurring basis. And what
you see is that in certain markets like
China, there are just different
preferences. And we're still working
through those and we want to make sure
we can cater to these markets in the
right way. China is such an important
market and I think paid trials will
probably, you know, it's not just China
that I've seen them in. I've seen them
in other parts like in Europe as well.
It's so fascinating and I mean I was
thinking as you were talking, I mean it
is a weird concept that that you're just
giving something away, something of
value. You you don't walk into a
restaurant like give me give me a bite
of that steak to see if I want the steak
or the fish. You know, I guess maybe an
ice cream counter like you can get
samples of the different flavors when
they have like 50 flavors. Like there
aren't just there just aren't that many
places where you just get something
that's truly about It's a weird thing to
like give something that you're going to
charge for that should be truly valuable
but then just give it away, give it give
give the free taste away. So, yeah, I
can understand culturally and and just
like user psychology. And and I have
heard from you especially for folks who
are running ads, the signal of a you
know, $1 30-day trial kind of thing is
like the people who are willing to get
with that hurdle to a dollar can give
you on the day one much better signal
back to the ad networks than running a
free trial. So, I've even heard paid
trials being used for that reason as
well of just getting better signal
quicker because if you're willing to pay
a dollar, you're at least like willing
to pay something for the product. And
it's you know so many free trials these
days, people just turn them off
immediately after starting the free
trial. And so it's hard to like get
signal from a free trial. That's very
true. And I I would just say like the
the the day zero cancellation is such an
important like kind of thing to track if
you're ever running a free trial because
it's a good indicator of whether like
your users really have high intent or
not. Once they've canceled, it's really
hard to get them to un-cancel. And the
other thing is that like I think you
have to realize that if you don't earn
trust, then it's going to translate into
either just poor conversions or even
customer complaints that like oh I
didn't expect this charge. So super
important to get it right. Emil, so much
fun chatting with you today. It's a lot
of great lessons. So thank you so much
for joining. And anything you want to
share as we wrap up? Any jobs at
Duolingo you want to shout out? No,
thank you firstly for having me. Yep,
Duolingo is hiring. Please feel free to
look at our kind of careers website. And
if there's any roles that are of
interest, please apply. But thank you so
much again David for having me. Yeah,
thanks for joining me.
>> [music]
>> Thanks so much for listening.
If you have a minute, please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.